Speaker 1: What do we get out of this deal? The only thing we get out of it is the Japanese don't sell these bonds into the market. The Fed prevents that from happening. Why? Because the Fed is afraid, the U.S. government is afraid, that if Japan is selling treasuries, treasury prices are going to fall. And so to prevent that, we create inflation. That is what the Fed did. They created more money, gave it to Japan to use, to buy back yen, to increase the supply of dollars in circulation. that is more
Speaker 1: And in fact, if you look at what happened to the Fed's balance sheet in the most recent week, it rose by over $10 billion. And that isn't even the $10 billion that came from the Bank of Japan. That is $10 billion in U.S. Treasuries that the Fed went into the market and purchased.
Speaker 1: So the Fed is not only doing quantitative easing without acknowledging it, but it's doing it even worse because it's doing it on the part of the Bank of Japan, too. And if you think that's the end of the intervention, you're wrong. This is just the beginning.
Well, as you
Speaker 2: can see,
I am no longer in Connecticut. I
Speaker 3: am now back
Speaker 4: at sea and...
Speaker 4: I guess the rest of my podcasts for the next few weeks are going to be from my boat here. I am currently in Rhode Island, but I wanted to take some time out. Hopefully I don't lose the light. I had a busy day and I've had a lot that I wanted to speak about this week. So I finally made some time to talk about it because a lot of stuff has been happening. A lot of stuff that I have been predicting would happen is happening. And that's another reason why you want to watch TV.
Speaker 4: my podcast. Because when you watch my podcast, you don't get surprised by things. And the stuff that happens is stuff that I've been saying was going to happen. I don't just talk about it after the fact. I talk about it before the fact. Now,
the big
Speaker 4: news stories of the week that I'm going to
talk about today
Our
Speaker 4: number one, I'm going to talk about the jobs report, the July jobs report that came out earlier today. This is the first Friday of August, so we got the numbers for July. But also, and maybe even more important, is what happened in Japan, because what happened in Japan with the Japanese yen is pretty much what I've been warning about for many, 20 months on this podcast that I saw a potential financial crisis brewing.
Speaker 4: in japan and i think the united states government the federal reserve agreed with me and so
Speaker 5: they took unprecedented action to try to postpone uh that crisis to to try to hold off a day of reckoning i don't think it's going to work yeah they kicked the can one more time but
Speaker 4: the problem is much too big as i have been saying but before i get into the japan stuff
i'm
Speaker 4: I'm going to start with the markets, just what happened
Speaker 5: with the markets in response to both of these things. The jobs report, the much weaker than expected jobs report, which
Speaker 6: I've been, you know, warning that that was going to happen. And I think what happened with Japan. But it was a big week in the markets. And of course, the mainstream media is mostly going to talk about the stock market. And yeah, the stock market was up. The Dow was up.
Speaker 6: about 1.8% on the week, S&P up
Speaker 4: 3%, NASDAQ up 4.7%,
Speaker 5: so a rebound in a lot of the tech stocks this week, not all, but most of them, Russell 2000 up 3.2%, but the real action was in precious
Speaker 7: metals, and I have been pounding the table on this podcast to buy gold and silver as they were near support.
Speaker 7: Gold was hanging out around 4,000 support for many, many weeks, a couple of months now. A couple of times it dipped below 4,000, but not by much. And it never really stayed there for more than a day. And I kept saying 4,000 was support. You got to buy it. Well, this week, gold closed at 4,341, up 7.8% on the week. Silver...
had
Speaker 7: an even better week, up 12.3%, closing at 63.46. Now, it had support in the mid-50s to upper 50s. I kept saying that was support. I kept saying that I did not expect silver to trade back below 50, that days of sub-$50 silver were over, that this $50 ceiling,
Speaker 7: that had restrained silver going back to 1980, and then again in 2011, that that ceiling had been shattered, that that resistance was now support, and I didn't expect anybody to get another shot at buying silver below 50, that you were going to have to pay up, and if you didn't pay up, you didn't get in. Now, of course, even 63 is still about half of the new record high that we set, I think it was the end of February.
Speaker 6: this year. So we're going to go back up there. But this is still a great time to be buying silver.
Speaker 4: The miners had an even better week. And
Speaker 5: again, I've been telling everybody to pick up these miners. They were on sale. The GDX was up 22% on the week, one week, 22%. That's like three years of decent stock market gains in one week.
and
Speaker 5: that's why you don't want to finesse this thing and try to be cute these stocks can really move the gdxj which has a little bit smaller market cap than the gdx up 25 percent on the week now of course there's still a long way to go i mean if you missed out on last week it doesn't mean you can't buy the miners i think they're still going a lot higher but i have been saying on this podcast
Speaker 4: week after week after week.
buy
Speaker 4: these stocks. And this was a week that you were really rewarded if you did.
Now, as I
Speaker 4: said, if
you're
Speaker 5: stuck with Bitcoin, I've been telling everybody, get rid of Bitcoin, get into the miners. Bitcoin was only up 3.7 percent on the week. It was up less than the Nasdaq.
It was
Speaker 5: up half of what gold was up, a third of what silver was up.
Speaker 5: Talk about the fastest horse in the race. That's what everybody has been saying ever since Paul Tudor Jones made that statement. Bitcoin is the slowest horse in the race. If you're still on Bitcoin before they send it out to the glue factory, get off and get
on a
Speaker 6: real horse, a hi-ho silver, get on the silver horse, the gold horse, or get on the miners, get out
Speaker 4: of Bitcoin now.
Speaker 4: Strategy did bounce on the week, 9%, so not a bad move. But once again, another week, they announced on Monday, another week where they sold not only strategy stock, but they sold more Bitcoin to raise cash so
Speaker 5: that they can pay stretch. And in fact, Michael Saylor came out on X and reposted something, I think from the CEO of strategy, that the primary mission
of
Speaker 5: strategy right now is to get stretch to trade between 99 and 100. So forget about a fiduciary responsibility
Speaker 6: to maximize the gains of the common stockholders. Those objectives have now been subordinated to the preferred. So if you own micro strategy stock, your interests have been subjugated to the preferred. The real goal isn't to maximize
the
Speaker 6: The return for the common shareholders, but the preferred shareholders. And if we have to sacrifice and
Speaker 8: dilute common, so be it. So you're just a sacrificial lamb
Speaker 1: waiting to get slaughtered if you hold on to that stock. I mean, if you like Bitcoin and, you know, you should like it. But if you like Bitcoin, then just stay in Bitcoin. There is no reason to buy a strategy because the company no longer is even looking out for your interest. They are willing to do
Speaker 1: deals that are dilutive. In fact, the year to date, I think Bitcoin yield now is down to three and a half percent. It was 13.3% two and a half months ago. And all these dilutive transactions have destroyed almost all of
the Bitcoin
Speaker 1: yield that Saylor was bragging about generating earlier in the year. So the very metrics that he used to say that you're supposed to judge him by, he now fails.
Speaker 1: And of course he doesn't even mention those metrics anymore. Anyway, the bigger story
Speaker 5: though,
Speaker 7: I think
Speaker 5: was the failure of the bond market to rally. Even though we got weaker than expected jobs numbers today, the yield on the 10 year treasury barely slipped. It went down to 4.66 from 4.69,
hardly anything.
Speaker 5: And the yield on the 30 year,
Speaker 5: went down a tick from 5.22 at the end of last week to 5.21 at the end of this week. So no relief,
Speaker 4: even with a drop in oil prices, which fell. Oil closed about 77, so down, I think, for the second week in a row. You know, we were up at $90 a barrel.
Speaker 4: But now all this talk about a
Speaker 7: deal, which again, who the hell knows if there's any kind of deal or if it's, you know, how lousy this deal is going to be. But there's a new ceasefire. They're talking about opening up the Strait of Hormuz, whatever. But all that positive, you know, de-escalation piece and deal talk. Yes, oil prices came down, but not bond yields. That shows you how weak the bond market is.
Speaker 7: The dollar index was down on the week, down again today on the jobs
Speaker 4: numbers. So we closed at 99.6 on the U.S. dollar index. So that basically wraps up, I think, the most significant market moves. But the market
Speaker 5: reacted to the de-escalation, not just of war,
but
Speaker 5: of the
Speaker 4: ratcheting down of the expectations for Fed rate hikes. I think now the odds of any rate hikes at all between now and the end of the year, not just between now and September, but between now and the end of the year, it's about a coin toss, a 50-50 shot as
to
Speaker 5: whether or not there are going to be any rate hikes at
Speaker 7: all in 2026.
Speaker 7: And that is not only because
Speaker 4: of the weakness in the jobs market, but because of what happened in Japan. And again, what happened with jobs, what happened in Japan is exactly
Speaker 5: what I have been predicting would happen with both of those markets. This stuff does not surprise me. I've been waiting for this.
Speaker 5: I've been warning that it was coming, and this is the
Speaker 4: week that those forecasts were vindicated. And I expect many more of my forecasts to be vindicated in the weeks ahead. Anyway, I'm going to take a quick break for a commercial, and then on the other side, I'm going to come right back and get into first the jobs numbers, and then after that,
Speaker 9: we're going to go into the unprecedented action regarding Japan.
Speaker 10: there's a lot i should be doing for my health but hydration is one of the few things that makes an instant difference when i'm staying on top of it i feel better i have more energy and i'm just more ready for the day drip drop has made it easier to stay hydrated because it tastes great works fast and i can bring it with me wherever i go it's doctor developed proven fast hydration because hydration isn't just something you do when you're behind it's how you stay ahead
Speaker 10: Drip Drop uses science-based formulas for rapid hydration, so you feel results fast while getting three times the electrolytes of leading sports drinks. Drip Drop is trusted by firefighters, medical professionals, and over 90% of top college and pro sports teams because it's built to hydrate you faster and more effectively.
Speaker 10: than water alone. Perfect for staying active all summer long. Drip Drops Zero Sugar Plus is a breakthrough, fast-absorbing formula with an advanced blend of six key electrolytes, 15 essential vitamins and nutrients, and no sugar or artificial sweeteners. It's fast hydration built with what matters most. And honestly, all of their products
Speaker 10: tastes amazing. There are 16 original flavors and eight zero sugar plus options. I love the Cherry Limeade. And Drip Drop is a daily routine product, not just for workouts. To make it easy, Drip Drop has flexible subscription options. So you're never stuck without proven fast hydration. Right now, Drip Drop is offering podcast listeners
Speaker 6: 20% off your first order. Go to dripdrop.com
Speaker 6: and use promo code GOLD. That's DripDrop.com, promo code GOLD for 20% off. All right,
Speaker 5: so today we got the July non-farm payroll number. And remember, we got the number for June last month and it was a miss. And there was the expectation that we would have a bit of an improvement from the very
Speaker 4: week,
Speaker 4: report that we got last month, just 57,000 jobs, they were expecting, I forget, maybe 100,000 or something like that. And it was a miss. And the expectations was for an improvement in July. The median was 88,000 new jobs, but the range went from
Speaker 9: 50,000 on the low end to 140,000 on the high end.
The
Speaker 9: actual number of
Speaker 5: jobs reported for July was minus 23,000 jobs. So a loss of jobs, negative 23,000, adding insult to injury. They revised down
Speaker 4: the 57,000 jobs from June to just 20,000 jobs. So it was an even bigger miss than they originally thought. And in fact,
If you
Speaker 4: look at the two months
Speaker 5: combined, there's a net loss of 3,000 jobs over two months. And again, who knows where the July number is going to end up? Because they could revise this thing a lot lower. We're starting at minus 23,000. Who the hell knows where we're going to end up? And in fact, when it comes to the revisions, they revised down the month before as well, May,
January.
So
Speaker 5: the total revisions for the prior months was another 105,000 jobs that were taken away. These are jobs that they originally reported as being created, and they took those jobs away so that they don't exist. Now, if you recall, originally in
May, the
Speaker 5: report was 173,000 jobs.
Speaker 5: jobs. And that was a beat because the original estimate for May was 105,000 jobs created, right? That's what they originally estimated were created in May. So when they came out with 173,000, everybody was excited, right? Wall Street was excited. Donald Trump was excited. What was I saying
On
Speaker 5: the
Speaker 8: podcast, I did the day those jobs numbers came out. I said, "Hold the champagne. This number means
nothing." Who
Speaker 5: knows what it's actually gonna be? You can't celebrate the original number because it's gonna be revised. And based on history, it's gonna be revised down. I mean, 'cause they're almost always revised down. And in fact, that main number
has
Speaker 5: now been
Speaker 8: revised down twice last month and again this month. So that number now stands at 63,000.
Given the fact
Speaker 8: that the original estimate was 105,000, it wasn't a beat at 173,000, it was a
Speaker 1: miss. It was 63,000 versus 105,000 expectations. So the markets reacted to the news as if, oh, we have a stronger labor market than we thought.
Speaker 1: But we actually had a weaker labor market than they thought, except we didn't find that out for a couple of months, except it should have been obvious two months ago, just like it was obvious to me that the number was meaningless, that the opening bid means nothing. They're going to revise it down. And that is exactly what they did. Now, when you look at the numbers that we got today, again,
the
Speaker 11: deeper you look, the worse they
look.
Yes,
Speaker 4: the unemployment rate fell to 4.1%. And, you know, maybe
Speaker 5: Trump will brag about that.
But the
Speaker 5: question is, why did it fall? It
fell because
Speaker 5: the labor force participation rate went down to 61.4%. Now, the last time it was that low was in early 2021. Now, what was going on?
Speaker 5: During early 2021,
Speaker 7: the economy was still in COVID lockdown.
Think about
Speaker 7: all the people who left the
Speaker 8: labor force because the whole economy was locked down. You have to go down to that period to find a labor force participation this low. So
in other
Speaker 8: words, the real reason that the unemployment rate went down isn't because unemployed people found jobs. No, it's because
Speaker 7: unemployed people found jobs.
Speaker 7: just left the labor market because they realized that there were no jobs. Now,
if
Speaker 5: you don't count the COVID lockdown period,
in order to
Speaker 5: find another point in
Speaker 6: time where the labor force participation rate
was as
Speaker 6: low as it is right now,
you got
Speaker 6: to go back 50 years, 50-year
Speaker 5: low in labor force participation. So clearly, we have a weak balance
Speaker 5: jobs market. We're losing jobs. In fact, full-time jobs dropped again.
Speaker 7: We lost another 106,000 full-time jobs in July. And
now we've
Speaker 7: lost full-time jobs in America in the last six of the seven months, full-time
Speaker 5: jobs destroyed. And also, you know, adding insult to injury, look at the average hourly earnings.
Speaker 5: which were supposed to rise by 3.5%, only rose by 3.2%,
workers are not
Speaker 5: earning more money. I mean, they're not keeping up with inflation. And in fact, I was
Speaker 7: listed as some guy, I think he was from J.P. Morgan Asset Management. He was on CNBC today. And
Speaker 1: he was saying that, you know, because we're not seeing the strong wage growth, that the Fed should not do anything about inflation.
Speaker 1: because we don't have the ingredients for like a wage price spiral because we're not having wages really going up. And so the Fed doesn't have to hike rates because, you know, inflation hasn't spilled
Speaker 7: over in the labor market, which is a bunch of nonsense because inflation is even worse, I guess, if it doesn't spill over in the
Speaker 8: labor market. Because if you're a worker, you're
Speaker 8: If prices are going up, you would hope that your wages are going to go up, too. That's like some consolation. But if you have your cost of living going up, if food is getting more expensive, energy, insurance, health care, everything you're buying is going up, but your wages are not, the inflation is even a bigger problem for you.
Speaker 8: To the extent that inflation is more concentrated in goods and not labor, that's not good for workers. That's actually bad for workers. And that means that inflation is a bigger problem. The Fed should work harder to get rid of it if people's wages are not also going up. I mean, maybe if your wages were keeping pace with prices, it wouldn't be as big a problem for you. Now, it would be a big problem for retirees who are living on a fixed income. But if the workers are seeing wages
Speaker 8: going up, at least commensurate with prices, then at least they're treading
Speaker 7: water. They're not sinking. But what's happening now is prices are going up
Speaker 5: faster than wages. And now you've got this guy, JP Morgan, saying, hey, there's nothing to worry about. Let's let that problem take care of itself. No, that problem is actually worse. So the bottom line, though, is the jobs market is weak.
Speaker 8: It has always been weak.
Speaker 8: Anybody who is saying that we have a strong labor market is wrong.
And in fact,
Speaker 8: look what's happening with college grads. I saw a chart today that I think we have fewer college grads working now than a couple of years ago. People are having a hard time with these college degrees. Meanwhile, their student loans are at record highs. So they're borrowing record amounts of money to get these degrees. And then they can't even get jobs to pay back the
Speaker 1: money.
Speaker 1: that they borrowed in order to get these worthless degrees. So we have this weak labor market, but what's even more significant is that it's happening in the context of high inflation. It's not like the weak jobs market is restraining prices.
Speaker 1: Prices are going up because the Fed continues to create inflation to push them up. So this is stagflation. Again, this is why Donald Trump is so unpopular. His popularity now is down to, I think,
Speaker 5: 33%.
The only
Speaker 5: president who has been this unpopular was Richard Nixon in the weeks before he resigned in disgrace. What does that tell
you?
If
Speaker 8: the economy was half as good as Trump claims, his popularity would not be this low. He would be getting credit for the economy.
Speaker 5: Instead, he's being blamed for the economy because the economy is bad. See, when it's good, you get credit. But when it's bad, you get blamed. And that's what's happened. Same thing with
Speaker 8: consumer confidence. But also look at the net debt, household debt, the savings rate. People are struggling.
Speaker 8: Just to get by. They are, you know, using up what meager savings they have left to handle the rising cost of living. And nobody
Speaker 6: cares. You know, in fact, Donald Trump was talking again today because he's got this court battle over the White House ballroom.
And
Speaker 6: this $400 million
Speaker 4: they're spending. And, you know, supposedly, you know, the money's being gifted, you know, donations. Well, who knows what people expect to receive in return for these donations. But Donald Trump keeps talking about this as if it's this great
Speaker 5: gift to the American people. This ballroom that we're creating is a gift to the American people. How are the American people going to benefit from this ballroom?
Speaker 8: How does turning the White House into a palace, how does that benefit the American people?
Speaker 7: I mean, the reason we call it a White House, right, as opposed to a palace, is it's supposed to house a citizen president. That's what the framers wanted. We don't have royalty in this country, right? We don't have fancy ballrooms in our White House. It's just a house. Yes, it's a big house.
But
Speaker 7: it's where the president lives. He lives there for a while.
Speaker 8: He's a common man. He's not royalty. He's president for a while. He's called Mr. President, right? Not your royal highness, just Mr. President. And Mr. President
Speaker 1: lives in the White House. And then he goes back to his own house.
We
Speaker 1: don't need a palace. We don't need a ballroom so that we can have balls, especially when most Americans
are
Speaker 8: struggling just to put food on the table for Trump to say, this is a great gift to America, this ballroom that you're never going to see because you're not going to get
Speaker 1: invited to this ball, right? You're not Cinderella. You're not coming to the ball. This is for the Washington elite so that they can party, so that they can celebrate,
so
Speaker 1: How is this a gift to America? What Americans need is more freedom. They need less government. So Donald Trump should be focusing on the real problems confronting Americans, not the fact that we don't have a ballroom in the White House. I mean, I'm glad there's no ballroom there and I'm upset at the fact that we're now creating. You know, talk about, you know, Nero fiddling while Rome burns or a let them eat cake kind of Marie Antoinette
Speaker 7: moment here.
Speaker 7: This
Speaker 5: shows how out of touch Donald Trump really is if he thinks the most important thing on the minds of
Speaker 7: the American public is whether or not there's a ballroom so that people in Washington can can go to more balls and have more celebrations
Speaker 8: in Washington as they are struggling on Main
Speaker 1: Street. But, you know, I think even more significant than the.
Speaker 1: jobs report, the weak jobs report that, you know, is in line with my forecast, more significant is what happened in Japan. And again, if you've been listening to my podcast, I have been talking about this for months. In fact, some of my titles to my podcast have focused on Japan. Hardly anybody has been paying attention to Japan until what just happened this week. And even
Speaker 1: Based on what happened, hardly anybody is paying attention to it because they don't perceive the significance of what just happened. Now, maybe gold and
Speaker 8: silver buyers in a way, that's why you had this explosive move up in gold and silver this week. But I think there's a lot more coming as this story plays out because it's far from over.
Speaker 8: What just happened may be unprecedented, but it's
Speaker 1: not the end. It's just the beginning. So I got one more commercial break. So stick around and I'm going to get to what happened with Japan
Speaker 9: on the other side of the break.
One of the
Speaker 10: biggest growth hacks is realizing you don't have to do it all yourself. Upwork makes it easy to bring in the right freelancer when you need them. So you can stay focused on what you do best. Upwork is a one-stop platform to find, hire, and pay expert freelancers across web and
software.
Speaker 10: software development, data and analytics, marketing, business operations, and more. Upwork helps grow your business by giving you fast access to specialized talent across over 125 categories. So you can fill skill gaps, launch projects faster, and scale support up or down without committing to full-time headcount. You can browse profiles, review past work,
Speaker 10: and get help scoping the role so you can hire with confidence and get started quickly. With Business Plus, you can access the top 1% of talent on Upwork. And with AI-powered shortlisting, you'll get matched to the right freelancer in under six hours. No endless searching required. Upwork also cuts down operational hassle by handling things like contracts and payments in one place so you can spend more time running the business. Thousands of growing businesses already trust Upwork to hire flexible, high-quality
Speaker 10: freelance talent for everything from one-off projects to ongoing support it's free to sign up and posting a job is easy visit upwork.com right now and post your job for free that is upwork.com to connect with top talent ready to help your business grow that's upwork.com upwork.com okay
now i have
Speaker 4: been talking about the problem in japan for many many months now in particular Thank you,
sir.
Speaker 4: How the problems in Japan potentially could cause a real crisis in the United States. Now, the problem they were having in Japan, the Japanese yen fell to a 40-year low against the dollar. You could buy over 163 yen for one dollar.
The
Speaker 4: weakness in the yen was translating into rising Japanese government bond yields. The yield on the 30-year Japanese government bond hit an all-time record high, just under 4%. The Japanese didn't even start issuing that bond, I think, until earlier in the 2000s. But the 10-year JGB, which they had been issuing for a long time, the yield there rose to about a 30-year high.
Speaker 4: Inflation
is a
Speaker 4: problem in Japan. Now, they were acting as if deflation was a problem, although they didn't really have deflation. They just had low inflation. But now they don't have low inflation anymore. Inflation is a big problem in Japan, yet the Japanese government
Speaker 7: is doing nothing about
Speaker 5: it because over
Speaker 7: the prior couple of decades,
Speaker 7: the japanese government sold so many bonds in order to supposedly revive inflation which was a huge goal they said we don't have enough inflation which was always bs
but they
Speaker 7: were
Speaker 5: really trying to uh keep the yen from rising they were trying to prop up zombie companies from the bubble that burst decades ago they were trying to help their exporters by weakening their currency
Speaker 5: Well, they actually turned huge trade surpluses into
Speaker 7: deficits. They undermined their economy with their easy money policies. I was a critic of
Speaker 1: Abenomics the entire time that they were pursuing it and everything they've been doing in Japan since that huge bubble burst towards the end of the 1980s. But they accumulated so much debt, their debt to GDP is
Speaker 8: well over 200%.
Speaker 8: And I was talking about the spiral where Japan had to do something. Interest rates in Japan, their policy rate, which is the equivalent
Speaker 1: of our Fed funds rate, is 1%. How do you have a 1% Fed funds rate when your 30-year yields are 4%? You have a steep yield curve, and you've got inflation that's well north of 2%.
Who
Speaker 1: knows where, you know, they probably have the same phony numbers over there. I'm sure, you know, we don't have a monopoly. I'm lying to the public about how much the cost of living is going up. And we know, look, Japan imports all their energy, almost all their food, right? The yen is collapsing. Food prices are rising. Energy prices
Speaker 7: are rising. This is a big problem. And I knew that something was going to happen here because
Speaker 8: they need to start propping up the yen.
And one
Speaker 8: way to do that is with intervention. But
how do
Speaker 8: they intervene? They need to sell dollars and buy yen. Well, the Japanese just don't have a bunch of dollars sitting around. They use their dollars to buy U.S. Treasuries.
They
Speaker 8: own more U.S. treasuries than any other country. They're our number one creditor. They have like 1.1 trillion of treasuries. And I would say, hey, the Japanese are going to start selling treasuries. The treasury market is already weak. What happens when they start selling? And if they're able to get the yen to go up
and the
Speaker 8: markets believe the yen is turning, which is what they need, now you're going to start to unravel that.
Speaker 8: the yen carry trade,
Speaker 1: especially if the Bank of Japan raises interest rates, which they should have done, but they did not do that. They met earlier in the week and they left interest rates unchanged. I think it was Monday or Sunday night our time. They announced no change in policy. Now they did indicate that maybe between now and the end of the year that rates could go up by 25 basis points. Big deal.
Speaker 1: from 1% to one and a quarter, ain't going to cut it. They need substantial hikes. I said on a prior podcast, even 2%. They need at least 3%. I don't even think that'll do it. But they got to get up there. But they can't because they're stuck in a box because they already have
so much
Speaker 1: debt. Now, I mentioned the Japanese people,
are
Speaker 1: wealthy. They have a lot of savings. Japan is the third biggest creditor nation in the world. They used to be number one, but these asinide policies reduced it two notches. Now Germany is number one and China is
Speaker 8: number two and Japan is number three, but they're still net creditors. Japan can still afford to do the right thing, yet they still won't do it. I mean, we can't afford it. That's why we'll
Speaker 1: never do it.
But
Speaker 1: Japan might, but so far they're not. They did not raise rates. Now, I think one of the reasons that the Fed did not hike rates at its last meeting was because they were doing a favor for Japan and not necessarily a favor that didn't benefit them. They were indirectly doing it to benefit themselves because the Bank of Japan probably didn't want to hike rates for obvious reasons.
So they
Speaker 1: probably discussed this with with the Fed and said, look, if you hike rates, we're going to have to hike rates. We don't want to. But if you hike rates and we don't, the yen is really going to get killed and we can't allow that. Or we're going to have to dump treasuries if that's the case. So you got to work with us here and you got to not hike rates because we don't want to have to hike rates. And if you leave rates unchanged.
Speaker 1: Then we can leave our rates unchanged because the big difference is the rate differentials, especially with the carry trade. So if the U.S. raised interest rates, that would have hurt the yen and put Japan in a position where they either had a hike rates, which they didn't want to do, or they would have to sell a lot of U.S. treasuries, which the U.S. didn't want them to
do.
So I
Speaker 1: think that is another reason,
Speaker 5: not the only reason, that we didn't get a rate hike. Even though Powell and the Fed, they're all talking tough about fighting inflation, yet they refuse
Speaker 7: to raise rates to actually do it. Well, that's another reason. But here is the bigger deal.
Japan told
Speaker 7: the United States
that we
Speaker 7: need to intervene in the currency markets. So we got to sell dollars to buy yen.
which
Speaker 7: means we've
Speaker 1: got to sell treasuries to get those dollars. Now, the Fed, probably talking with the Treasury Department, was like, no, you can't do that, right? The bond market is tanking. The last thing we need is big sales by Japan, right, to push it over the edge that it's teetering on. So the U.S.
Speaker 8: government, right, made a deal with Japan, said, hey, you don't have to sell those treasuries. Let's just do a repo with us. Let us buy those treasuries from you,
Speaker 8: And then you can buy them back from us later
Speaker 1: on. It's like a swap. You give us treasuries and we'll give you dollars. So you don't have to actually sell your treasuries to get dollars. We'll just take the treasuries off your hands and we'll give you dollars. And that is what happened.
And so
Speaker 1: the Bank of Japan or Japan, whatever, got the dollars it needed not by selling the treasuries,
But
Speaker 1: by giving the treasuries to the U.S., and the Fed just cranked up the printing presses or, you know, created the money that they need. It was like $10 billion, right, that Japan had to then sell into the market to buy back yen. So this is a form of quantitative easing. It's just that the Fed is not going into the market and buying those $10 billion of treasuries. The Fed is...
Speaker 1: taking the 10 billion of treasuries from Japan and then creating the money and giving it to Japan. And the crazy thing about it is, Japan still earns the coupon on those treasuries. So they don't have to sell with treasuries. They get the dollars without selling them. They still get the coupon. So the United States is still paying
Japan.
Speaker 1: interest on the treasuries that it doesn't even really have anymore that it
sold
Speaker 8: back to the Fed now Japan has to pay interest on the money that it borrowed because the treasuries are their collateral so Japan has to pay interest on that loan but the interest is
Speaker 1: paying is lower than the coupon it's getting so it's still a positive carry so it works out great for Japan because they get the dollars they need
And
Speaker 1: they're still making some cash flow on the treasuries that are parked at the Fed.
But what do we
Speaker 1: get out of this deal?
The only thing
Speaker 1: we get out of it is the Japanese don't sell these bonds into the market. The Fed prevents that from happening. Why? Why?
Speaker 1: Because the Fed is afraid, the U.S. government is afraid that if Japan is selling treasuries, treasury prices are going to fall. And so to prevent that, we create inflation. That is what the Fed did. They created more money.
Speaker 1: Gave it to Japan to use, to buy back yen, to increase the supply of dollars in circulation. That is more inflation. And in fact, if you look at what happened to the Fed's balance sheet in the most recent week, it rose by over $10 billion. And that isn't even the $10 billion that came from the Bank of Japan. That is $10 billion in U.S. treasuries that the Fed went into the market and purchased.
Speaker 1: So the Fed is not only doing quantitative easing without acknowledging it, but it's doing it even worse because it's doing it on the part of the Bank of Japan too. And if you think that's the end of the intervention, you're wrong. This is just the beginning. Because if the Bank of Japan keeps interest rates down at 1%, the pressure on the yen is going to continue. And if the pressure on the yen is going to continue, then more intervention is going to be required. Now look, the last
Speaker 8: time,
that
Speaker 8: the U.S. government intervened to support the Japanese yen was 1998. That was 28 years ago. So this is not something that happens, you know, routinely. And the intervention that they just did was 10 times bigger about than what they did in 1998. So the scale is certainly unprecedented. The U.S. government has never intervened to this degree.
And the
Speaker 8: fundamentals haven't changed. The currency speculators can see this. They're going to continue to push the envelope here and sell off the Japanese yen. And so Japan is going to have to keep intervening. But the only way Japan can get money to buy yen is to sell treasuries. Now, we've made it clear we don't want them to sell treasuries.
Speaker 8: So we're just gonna keep the swap lines open. We're gonna keep allowing the Japanese government to bring
Speaker 7: its treasuries over to us and,
you know,
Speaker 7: do these repos so that they can get a bunch of dollars that we create out of thin air and use those dollars to buy Japanese yen. Now, the other unprecedented aspect of what just happened is that we didn't even sell dollars.
To
Speaker 8: buy yen, we used our euros, not our dollars. So we used up, I don't know, it was probably most of our euros. I'm not
Speaker 7: really sure. I forget how many euros we've got. I mean, the U.S. has foreign exchange reserves.
But
Speaker 7: they're very small, you know, relative to the size of our economy. And that's because, you know, we don't think we really need FX reserves. After all, we got the reserve currency. So why do we need other reserves? Why the hell do we need euros or yen or pounds where we can create all the dollars we need?
Speaker 7: Other countries have bigger foreign reserves because they don't have the reserve currency. So they need our currency as a reserve against theirs. But we don't have the reserve against our currency because our currency is the reserve. But nonetheless, we have foreign exchange reserves. Well, instead of using dollars to buy yen, we used euros. Now, why did we do that? Because I think that the U.S. government was afraid
Speaker 8: to use dollars because that would have driven the dollar much lower, which probably would have driven bond yields higher because selling dollars
Speaker 7: would have been more inflationary because of the implications for the dollar. And so the U.S. government decided to do this intervention, this time using euros.
Speaker 8: Now,
Speaker 8: There's a limit to how long we can use euros because we run out of euros.
Speaker 1: Now, we don't run out of dollars because we can print as many as we want. Of course, what they're going to be worth is a whole different story. We can't determine what they buy. We just can create as many as we want. The market doesn't have to accept them. But, you know, the ECB.
had
Speaker 1: no idea this was happening, right? They were completely blindsided. So the Fed didn't give them a heads up, right? That, hey, or the Treasury Department did say, look, you know, we're gonna be selling the Euro, you know, no offense guys, you know, we don't mean anything by it, but we're gonna be dumping your currency so that we can help out Japan and prop up the yen because they found out about it when everybody else found out about it after the fact. And obviously they were not happy about the fact
Speaker 1: that their own currency was sold off. By the way, the euro rebounded. So this intervention didn't even hurt the euro. But obviously, had the Fed intervened with dollars, the euro would be a lot higher. And so I think that the Fed was cognizant of this. And so they tried to get away with the intervention by using euros.
But
The
Speaker 1: ability to do this with euros or other currencies is going to run out. So I think what's going to be happening is you're going to see more interventions, more swaps, repurchase agreements between Japan and the United States.
Speaker 1: but there's going to be more intervention to, from. It's not going to be just Japan, right? It needs to be coordinated intervention, right? This is a big job that they're trying to do here, holding off the markets. So all this intervention, money printing, quantitative easing, this is completely inconsistent with a Fed that claims that it cares about inflation. Again, forget about what the Fed says. Look at what the Fed does.
The
Speaker 1: expansion of the balance sheet this week is inflationary. The failure to raise interest rates is
Speaker 7: inflationary. The repurchase agreements with Japan
Speaker 5: are inflationary. What they're doing is creating inflation.
Speaker 5: They're talking about fighting it, but they're actually creating it. So don't pay any attention to what they say. That's all a distraction. That's meant to cover up what they're
Speaker 4: actually doing, right? Like the Wizard of Oz. Don't pay any attention to that man behind the curtain, right? Just look up at the screen, right, to what you're seeing and ignore what's obviously going on behind the scenes.
And
Speaker 4: as I said earlier, that's why you're seeing this
Speaker 5: move up in gold and silver. This was a big week for gold and silver as far as the percentage
Speaker 4: gains. An even bigger week, obviously, for the mining stocks. But what's going to be happening now and over the next several weeks, several months, is I think you're going to start to see the expectations for Fed rate hikes coming down. Not because the Fed shouldn't hike rates. It absolutely
should.
Speaker 4: should hike
Speaker 5: rates, but they won't be able to because there's too many things going on to prevent them from doing what they
Speaker 8: should do. Now, they should do it anyway and just let the chips fall where they may. But they're not going to do that, you know, especially with the midterm elections coming up.
Speaker 7: They're not hiking rates.
Speaker 7: And, you know, after the midterm elections are over, in theory, I guess, you know, they could. But I think the problems are going to be even greater than
Speaker 8: in the economy, in the labor market. And the Japanese problems haven't been solved.
Speaker 7: They still have to raise rates substantially. And when they do that, that is going to spill over. So we're damned if they do and we're damned if they don't. the longer they try to avoid doing what they should, the more
they're going to
Speaker 7: have to intervene the more money the fed is going to have to print right the more repurchase agreements are going to have to be done so they're going to have to create all this inflation and eventually the bank of japan is going to have to start jacking up rates anyway and that still could create a financial crisis maybe the goal is to have the crisis happen after the midterm elections rather than before but that might be about the only thing that they're able to
do
is
Speaker 7: delay this day of reckoning. But I seriously doubt that they're going to delay it all the way through the end of the Trump term. And who knows
if Trump
Speaker 7: will even finish his term? I don't know what's going to happen. I mean, maybe he'll step down and Vance will finish it out. I don't really know because things are really going to get bad. And the president's popularity, as low as it is,
Speaker 7: is going to get lower i mean eventually it's going to start eating into his base there's only so much disappointment so many lies that they're ultimately going to be able to take but in the meantime oh wow really starting somebody just went by so uh the boat's really rocking around i picked up a little a little wake here um so in the meantime this is the lull before the storm
Speaker 6: right this week was a wake-up call right i don't know how much longer you got
but
But
Speaker 6: you really need to get your economic and your financial house in order because the economic storm that I've been forecasting is just over the
Speaker 7: horizon. It is coming. So you got to batten down the hatches because we are headed for a currency and a sovereign debt crisis. Yeah, you've got some positive things out there, too. You got all the potential productivity boom from AI, but before we can get to that valley,
Speaker 7: We got to go over this mountain. You know, we got all these problems that we are going to have to deal with. AI is not going to be a get out of jail free card, I don't think. I guess it's possible. Anything is possible. But I think you want to deal with the probable rather than just the possible. Yeah.
Speaker 7: And the probable is we got a big problem coming. We got bond crisis, currency crisis. We got to deal with it. Well, first, we got to prepare for it because we can't do anything about it because we've got no power. I've got no power. The average person listening to my podcast probably doesn't have
Speaker 1: any power, so we can't stop it.
We
Speaker 1: can warn about it. We can make sure that people know about it and, more importantly, know why. That's the message I want out there so that when it happens, it's not another 2008 financial crisis where they're able to blame it on capitalism, blame it on the corporations, blame it on, you know, not enough regulation. I want
people to
Speaker 1: know that this crisis was made by government.
Speaker 1: It's caused by government, not by capitalism, not by the free markets. And in fact, if you look right now at the rise in the popularity of the left, of the socialists on the left, they are gaining, gaining in popularity. AOC, Bernie Sanders, they are getting more and more popular as Trump
Speaker 7: is getting less popular because people are misassociating Trump with, you know, radical right.
Speaker 7: Too much
Speaker 1: capitalism when he is left, he is left of center. He is not a conservative, a libertarian. You know, he is a left wing Republican, not like Goldwater or Reagan, but more like Rockefeller, Nixon, except worse, except to the left.
not
Speaker 1: all of his policies, but a lot of his policies. And so I wanna make sure that people know that what Trump is doing, this is not free market capitalism. This is big government, and the crisis is not just the Republicans' fault, it's both parties. Both parties have been participating in creating this crisis for decades. And the question is, who's gonna be on the watch when everything comes crashing down?
And
Speaker 1: it could very easily be Trump and the Republicans and they get the blame. And unfortunately, it unfairly tarnishes what is associated with the Republicans, which is free market capitalism and then adds credibility to socialism, even though it's the socialist policies advanced by the Republicans that are the problem and the socialist concept of a central bank where you turn over.
Speaker 1: monetary policy to the government, where the government controls and sets interest rates, not the free market. There is nothing capitalistic about having a central bank. It's a socialist concept to say that we are going to turn over this responsibility to government. We're going to take it away from the free market, and we're going to allow government to determine these prices
Speaker 1: rather than allowing the free market to discover those prices. So when mistakes inevitably happen, it's not because of capitalism. It's because government failed to allow capitalism to prevent those mistakes from happening. But anyway, just want to wrap up this podcast. So hopefully I'll just leave everybody with, you know, you got to prepare. You got to make sure you've got, you know, your investments in order, your foreign stocks, your precious metals,
Speaker 1: positions and in the meantime tell your friends about about my podcast about my x account you got to follow me you got to listen to what i'm saying my podcasts are getting now more popular i'm noticing we've got 200 250 000 youtube views uh so make sure you're you know you're watching on youtube like and subscribe to the videos comment share with your friends i now have more than 1 2,650,000 ex-followers.
Speaker 1: I'm gaining three to 4,000 a day. This is a much bigger pace than I had six months a year ago. So the message is getting out there. I thank all of you who are helping me. Don't just follow me yourself, but repost everything I post. Make sure everybody who follows you sees what you're seeing, what I'm writing, especially now.
Speaker 1: Because so many of the things that I've been predicting are happening and they're happening for the reasons that I say they're going to happen. And so the mainstream media is going to keep, you know, spewing government propaganda. Well, I'm telling
Speaker 4: the truth. And, you know, there's a lot more of the propaganda out there than there is the truth. At least I've got these platforms and they can be a lot bigger.
Speaker 4: if you help me. Anyway, that's it for today's podcast. I'll be doing more podcasts from the boat as we continue cruising up the Atlantic. Eventually, I'm going to be in Maine. That's going to be the end of this trip. Again, I'm in Rhode Island now. We just left Connecticut. We're going to be up in Maine. And then from Maine, I'll be flying back to Puerto Rico. And then I'll be back in work mode from my studio by the end of this month, early September. I'll be back doing work. Anyway, hope you guys enjoyed this podcast. Bye for now.